Where is he?
That man in that photo.
My father, my master.
You knew my father?
Oh, yes, I knew your father.
Unfortunately, during the war.
-What is your name?
-My name is James Wright.
I was a wing commander,
Royal Air Force.
I spent time
with your father in Bataan.
My father
spoke of you.
Many stories about the Westerner
that knew the Eastern arts.
A great fighter.
A forbidden move.
But now, you come to my dojo,
revive shame for my family.
You bring trouble and dishonor.
Now, Mr. Wright,
I will give you trouble.
Stop!
What is it you've come here for?
Wait, wait, wait...
Let's go! Let's go!
British?
You, only survivor?
No survivors.
Another one.
How much? How much?
Shit.
Shit!
Oh, shit.
Move!
Wing Commander James Wright,
Royal British Air Force.
Corporal Hirano was
like a brother to me.
My sincerest condolences.
Sleep well,
Wing Commander Wright.
Today you are victorious,
but tomorrow, you die.
Move!
Randall J.
Priniger, Ludington, Michigan.
Most guys call me
"The Beard," or "Beardy,"
or just plain old "Beard."
I respond to all variations,
non-derogatory variations.
Good to meet you. Wright.
You got a first name, Wright?
Yes, James.
Royal Air Force. I'm a pilot.
This is the Greek's.
It's reserved for the Greek.
Come... Come, come,
come, come. Come here.
Take this one.
This was Simmons' spot.
He's gone now.
Yeah, he's dead.
He got the fucking malaria.
No, no, no. Dysentery.
The bloody flux.
How'd you get here, James?
Was sent on a support mission
to back up
the Allies' last stand.
There were ten of us,
we took off from a banana boat
on the South China Sea.
We were told that
the Filipinos had a foothold
in the peninsula,
but I guess that was bad intel.
By the time we arrived, the Japs
had pretty much wiped
everyone out.
Turned out to be
a bloody suicide mission.
I was hit, ejected over
the water, dead of night.
Somehow washed up here.
So the Brits, are they
coming to liberate us or what?
And you are?
Gabriel Villanueva,
United States Army,
Sergeant First Class.
-Nice to meet you.
-Good to meet you.
He's half-Filipino.
They sent him here to help
train the locals in Bataan.
-It's Ba-tah-ahn.
-That's what I said. Ba-tahn.
So the Brits, are they coming?
I'm afraid not.
They think I'm dead,
they think...
they think we're all dead.
So, no.
Inside the barracks,
we maintain military structure.
We all have rules.
We share work detail,
even burial detail.
Also, we have our commander
here as well.
Who's that? Who's the commander?
Captain Collins.
He's the highest rank among us.
He's down in the A-barrack.
You'll meet him tomorrow.
I don't think there will be
a tomorrow for me, old chap.
That could be any of us.
No, no. I...
I already killed three of
Ito's men, that he knows about.
I'm pretty sure
that by tomorrow,
Ito's got a bullet
with my name on it.
That's, unless anyone knows
a way out of here.
Getting out of the camp
isn't the problem.
It's getting back in
and realizing
there's nowhere else to go.
They all come back,
and that's when they get caught.
You're better off
going on the march.
What's the march?
Anyone strong enough
to work, they stay here.
They had us clear a runway,
now they got us
building a perimeter wall.
They're sending the rest
to another camp 60 miles north,
and they're calling
that the Death March.
What do we know
about this other camp?
- Anything?
- Very little.
Men are dropping
off along the way.
Ones who do make it,
God only knows
what's happening to them.
For all we know,
this is the easy way out.
Or maybe you'll get
lucky and get the sword.
Just better hope
it's a clean beheading.
Sometimes it takes more than
one swing to finish the job.
Yeah, right.
Don't listen to him.
That's Times Square.
When the lieutenant colonel
addresses the camp,
they line us up there.
It's also where
the battles happen.
The battles happen there.
Ito puts all the people
who misbehave center stage.
He puts them in there
with his guards.
He uses it as
a training ground for them.
Up! Now!
These men were caught
with extra rations
inside of their barracks.
An example must be made.
Fight to the death!
He will meet
his end soon enough.
You got rocks in your fist?
Captain.
-Collins.
-Captain. Good to meet you.
That was some impressive shit.
Glad you're on my side.
Drinks on me.
- Beardy.
- Yeah?
-A round for the Brit.
-I'm... way ahead of you.
Kaboom.
A couple sips
of this will cure any ailment.
So, uh...
What happened to your leg?
You okay?
Yeah, took some shrapnel
a few months back.
Believe it or not,
I was the lucky one.
As long as I can do
hard labor, I'll be all right.
Cheers, boys.
Cheers.
May we live to fight
another day.
Oh, yeah.
You like it?
-Tastes like bloody petrol.
-It's my recipe.
It's supposed
to taste like petrol.
Where are you from
in England, James?
I was born in Surrey,
but grew up in Hong Kong.
Hong Kong.
How does that happen?
My father worked there.
Textiles, but I moved back
to England when he passed.
So was Hong Kong
where you learned
all that chop-socky bullshit?
Something like that.
No, I've been lucky enough
to train in a few places.
Uh, Hong Kong, Thailand,
even Japan.
I've been here a while.
Nobody makes it out
of those battles.
Here we go.
You are a skilled fighter.
Who trained you in our ways?
-Did you train in Japan?
-I've trained many places.
You've already
revealed who trained you.
Your technique, most forbidden.
This belongs to you?
Yes.
Your father, war hero?
Mine, too.
Give it back to me.
Maybe you'll see
your father again.
My father's dead.
Then you will
definitely meet him again.
Rest well, Commander.
Tomorrow...
you die.
Let's go, Brit. You're up.
-James, would you like a drink?
-No, thanks.
Let's get this done.
Anyone got
any water?
Yeah, Beardy. Water.
Uh, thank you.
Ito's head must be
spinning right now.
Why didn't you finish him off?
Ito's men, they're just
doing as they're told.
They don't want to die
any more than we do.
Look, let's get
out of sight.
Come to my office.
Look.
Okay. Hang in there, okay?
Because in about a week,
they're going to march us
to another camp.
We'll be out of this hellhole.
Or to a worse one.
If we make it.
I won't make it with this knee.
We need a radio.
If our forces are
still off the coast,
there's a good chance
we could contact them.
You don't think
they know we're here?
Of course they know we're here.
They're not going to waste
good men to come get us.
We're casualties of war.
There's radios... in that tower.
Right?
I'm going to get one.
We're all in.
All right.
Tell me when.
All right, now.
What, you
think you can take me? Come on!
Get back!
-Get back!
-Hey, right here.
Sorry! Sorry! Okay, okay, okay.
Sorry.
Don't move.
Now.
Oh, shit.
Thank you.
Have you come to save us?
I'll do my best.
- Gabriel, talk to me.
- Hold, hold, hold.
Okay, now.
You know we can
only listen on that.
As soon as we try to send
a signal, we're done.
I know.
They'll toss
the barracks to find it.
They won't find it.
Then they'll start
torturing us until they do.
There's more than one
of these things up there.
All right? One of them could
have easily been misplaced.
I hope so.
We all need to get out of here,
and I'm not going
on any bloody march.
Yeah, I know.
You have anything to write with?
Yeah.
Good.
And you speak, right?
I understand more than I speak.
Me, too.
Write down anything you hear,
even if it's just words
that don't make any sense.
Okay?
Mind if I have one of those?
No.
Oh, my God.
You really think
your men are close, James?
We took off from the coast
70 nautical miles away.
How far can they really be?
They know
you all went down, though.
Yes. Well...
We have to hope.
It has come to my attention
that individuals
have been going
into areas of the camp
that are off-limits.
You're pointing
at the wrong man.
Now is the only chance
to save your life.
Who?
Lopez.
Let this be a lesson!
Hey, Jonesy.
You don't know nothing,
so stop assuming.
Those boys found a way
outside the fence
without getting caught.
I didn't know them boys.
Bullshit! You've been spider
fighting with those boys
-for weeks.
-Jesus, Beardy,
mind your business.
Look, did those boys find a way
outside the fence,
or didn't they?
-Tell me.
-Okay.
Maybe they did.
Okay, so you went with them?
No.
But they told you,
though, right?
I don't know anything else.
What do you think is going to
happen if you tell me the truth?
You think I'm going
to rat you out?
-Don't be stupid.
-Stupid.
If those boys found
a way outside the fence
without the guard seeing
them from the tower,
I want to know. Tell me.
There's nothing
but jungle out there.
Again, it's not hard
to get out of this place.
Just a matter of a blind spot
and a few snipped wires.
Where?
Shit.
You were gone too long.
You were gone way too long.
Okay.
Tell me something, Brit.
How's the bay looking?
It was dark.
There's a few fishing boats,
a Filipino gunner still smoking,
but the Americans are close.
Hey, how do you know?
I heard Navajo.
- Jesus, Navajo?
- Yes.
We used that back when
the campaign started.
It was hard to hear,
but I'm telling you,
it was definitely Navajo.
Those fuckers have been
chasing their tail,
trying to figure that out.
How did you understand it?
I didn't,
but I know what I heard.
- There was something else.
- What?
I found a glider.
Well, yeah, no surprise.
They were using them
a few months back
to fly men and artillery in.
It was a crash mission.
No one survived.
It could be a way
to make contact, right?
Right?
What do you mean,
like a way out?
- Yes.
- On a fucking glider?
Are you mad? They glide.
There's no fucking motor
in them.
Look, we did
training missions, right,
in the C-47s, tow planes.
Now, let's shift this.
Now, a skilled pilot
could fly low enough
to hook the tow line
on a glider with a flyby.
-I've seen it done.
-Yeah, maybe on a runway,
but not the jungle.
And the runway we cleared
is about a good mile from here.
All we need to do
is set up support posts
either side
of the tow line, right?
Now, if that pilot
comes in straight on
and there's no trees, rocks,
in the immediate vicinity,
50 yards in front,
then I'm telling you that that
glider will go up like that.
I guarantee it.
It sounds like a long shot.
It could be bad if we
don't make the connection.
It could be really bad,
but what's the alternative?
Staying here under
Ito's command?
Then we know
we're really fucked.
We have to do something, right?
And I say this is it.
I trust you.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yes, I heard you.
Okay. Okay.
What do you know...
about Navajo?
Navajo?
Yes.
Indian language.
I know the Americans use it.
You understand this language?
-Why would I understand it?
-You understand Japanese.
I understand fucking German,
too. What's your point?
You find out
if your American friends
understand Navajo,
you earn the favor with me.
Nobody understands Navajo
except the Navajo.
That's the bloody point.
And even if they did,
why would any of the men
want to help you or Japan?
Because saving one's own life
is powerful motivation.
So is saving one's own country.
None of you will ever see
your home, your families.
If you survive this camp,
then you face the march.
If you survive the march,
hell awaits you
on the other end.
Then I guess we have nothing
left to lose then, do we?
Then you will keep fighting.
Oh, I'll keep fighting.
You can keep lining up
your men one after another,
and I'll teach the lot of them,
but it won't be Navajo.
An attack is mounting!
The Americans are still close,
and with Wright still here,
the British are close, as well!
But it's coming!
I don't understand
Navajo too well,
but if my ears are hearing it...
then something is unfolding.
Bite on this. It will help.
They were lucky.
What is coming is much worse.
Uh, no, no, no.
Uh, stay still.
Please, stay still.
How long have I been here?
Nearly two days.
We gave you morphine
so you can sleep.
- How did I get here?
- Ito's men.
It's a strange request.
Only Japanese soldiers
get sent here.
Your wound, it's healing.
I'm not so sure
how long you will stay here.
What's your name?
Theresa.
You know, I've been
wondering about you, Theresa.
Why wonder about me?
You're a prisoner here?
Like us?
Yes.
Yes, a prisoner,
but... not like you.
You're very strong,
you stand up to Ito...
But maybe not that smart.
Yes.
Ah, you're probably right.
-Oh, no, no, please--
-I'm... I'm okay.
-Some... some water, please.
-Okay.
Thank you.
How long have you been here?
Three months.
They separate me from my family.
Forced me to work.
They told me
to help the Japanese,
but I cannot fight the diseases
with these conditions.
You know this place?
There's nothing.
Just jungles
surrounding this place.
No possibility of escape.
What about Ito?
Has he said anything?
Did you hear anything
that might help?
Ito grows paranoid.
I fear he will not let me
leave this place alive.
Now listen to me.
- I have to tell you something.
- Okay.
Uh... You may...
you may rest now.
What's happening?
A demonstration outside.
Teaching your men what happens
when escape attempts are made.
Your strength is returning.
It's getting there.
Good.
Another challenge awaits you.
Tonight, you rest,
-but tomorrow--
-Tomorrow I die.
Yes, I know.
Why are you doing this?
Why are you getting me healthy
just so you can kill me?
Why? Why, Commander Wright?
I witnessed your
empty-handed technique.
Your sensei taught you well.
You honor him.
You know, if you've already
shown me your best men,
I'm confident I'll make it home.
Eventually you'll just
run out of warriors.
Then what?
You and I?
You?
They're coming.
I listen to the Navajo words.
I do not understand them,
but I fear a convoy is coming.
You should all share that fear.
Why?
Because if this happens,
nobody will survive.
How you feeling?
Oh, you know...
Given the circumstances.
Ito must want you alive.
It would seem
that way, wouldn't it?
Although I can't figure out
if I'm driving him crazy
or just entertaining him.
Maybe a little bit of both,
after that last show you put on.
I've never seen
anything like that.
Have you seen this?
Seen what?
"To all Japanese
ranking officers
of the Japanese Imperial Army.
Be advised,
United States military
and its allies
shall hold harshly responsible
all actions that lead
to the abuse of POWs,
civilian internees,
and civilian non-combatants
who are not accorded
the dignity, honor,
and protection provided by
the rules and customs of war.
The United States military
has been furnished
with unimpeachable evidence
of the degradation
and brutality to which American
and Allied POWs
have been subjected to,
which are in violation
of the most sacred
code of military honor.
Signed,
General Douglas MacArthur."
Let me see that.
They did a flyby yesterday.
Plane dropped a payload
of those things.
They're everywhere.
Our military wants
everyone to know
that they got eyes
on us and them.
That's great news, huh?
I'm not so sure about that.
Why is that?
According to this,
Ito knows he's in deep shit
if the Allies liberate the camp.
If that American convoy
turns up here,
he's probably going
to go full kamikaze,
probably take us all with him.
- Hey.
- Jeez!
What the hell
are you doing here?
I had to see
the glider for myself.
You still think
it's a crazy idea?
Yeah, of course I do, but
we gotta make contact first.
Listen, as soon as we
send that transmit out,
the Japs are going to know.
You speak Tagalog,
though, right?
Yeah, I do, but so do the Japs.
-But they don't speak Navajo.
-Yeah, well, neither do you.
Right? Do you?
Of course not.
No, but I think I've got an idea
to get the conversation started.
Come on.
- Wait. Wait.
- For what?
-Wait. Wait.
-He's going to talk.
Shut up.
I don't want to kill you.
Understand?
Yes.
Okay.
Go. Go. Go.
Bloody hell.
Okay. Go back. Go. Go.
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
-Seven.
-Eight.
Nine.
-Ten.
-Eleven.
Twelve.
They saw you?
Something like that, yes.
What happened?
Don't worry. We have a plan.
A plan for what?
I'll tell you about it
in the morning.
Whatever happens
next, don't you do a damn thing.
Last night,
several prisoners
left their barracks
and attacked the guards.
I know he was not alone.
It was me.
You?
Yes.
Me alone.
You attack my guards, alone?
You've seen me do it before.
You've got the wrong man.
It was me.
I...
admire your courage, Wright.
But your captain,
he was caught in the act.
Show me.
Show you what?
Forbidden move.
No.
You do forbidden move on him,
or my guards kill him.
I will not kill
a helpless, innocent man.
I made it known
that breaking the rules
of the camp
is punishable by death.
You know what's waiting
for you after this, don't you?
-We are at war.
-We are prisoners of war.
-There are rules!
-In my camp,
there are only my rules.
No one challenges
my authority in my camp!
I challenged your authority
every time I set foot
on that mat!
Or maybe you are here
for just my entertainment.
Do not think that you
are beyond my control.
Why don't you set foot
on that mat with me?
Then we'll see who's in control.
Yes.
Come on.
That's it.
Come on. Make a move.
Your training
is not what I thought.
A wise fighter would know better
than to enter a battle
that he cannot win.
Let's finish this now!
Do something!
Do something! You're a coward!
You're a damn coward!
You're a coward!
Come, fix my hand.
Hey, you all right?
What happened?
We have to do it tonight.
Tonight?
You want to send
a radio signal out tonight?
Yes.
Beardy's identified
a Navajo word
that comes up a lot.
Right, Beardy?
-"Atsah. Atsah."
-"Atsah?" What does it mean?
We have no bloody idea.
But how about if
we pair that word
with some carefully selected
words in Tagalog, right?
The Japs will send themselves
nuts trying to figure it out.
By the time they
realize that "atsah"
has no actual meaning
relative to the message,
hopefully we'll have
gotten the point across.
Are you sure?
Look, once we send
the message, that's it.
They're going to know
that we have a radio.
They're going
to know our location.
Yes, that's why
we're going to send it
from the hilltop
outside the camp.
They'll probably think
it's the rebels.
Look, Ito is becoming
increasingly concerned
about an incoming attack.
With any luck, this will
send him over the edge.
No, no, no. James.
Yeah, yeah,
that'll be bad for us.
You said he's ready to go
full kamikaze.
-Keep him calm.
-Beardy,
if there's one thing
that I've learned,
in battle, it's the calm man
that you should fear the most.
Okay.
Go!
They're out there somewhere.
Okay, I pray this works.
Here we go.
Atsah. Atsah.
Atsah.
Yes. Keep going.
You're doing fine.
Atsah.
They're not gonna know.
It doesn't matter. They know
we're not Japs. Keep going.
Okay.
Atsah.
Sunrise.
Eagle has wings.
No engine.
10-4.
Yes!
-We gotta shut it down.
-No, no, no!
We need to give them a location.
Um, say, uh, C-47.
C-47.
We're gonna give away the plan.
How are they going
to know where we are?
-Bright light.
-Bright light. What? Why?
Just say "bright light."
Say it now.
Bright light. Bright light.
Jungle Eagle.
Copy that.
There are flares in the tower.
-Bright light. We can use them.
-Bright light. Okay. Okay.
You think they're going
to piece it together?
Look, they know
we're friendlies.
They know we're talking
under duress.
They'll piece it together.
We gotta get the men. Let's go.
Where is everyone?
Hurry! Hide the radio, quick.
-Shit.
-Hurry. Hide it.
- Gabriel?
- Yeah.
- You okay?
- Yeah, I'm... I'm good.
-Are you okay?
-Can you get free?
Where are we?
I don't know. Can you get out?
Can you free yourself?
No, we gotta get
out of here, though.
Theresa.
-What are you doing here?
-I'm getting you out of here.
What's happening out there?
Shortly after you were captured,
Allied planes began to fly over.
A new battle has begun.
The plane has crashed.
Ito has gone mad.
He's killing everybody.
- Oh, my gosh.
- That's it.
Yes.
-You okay?
-Yeah.
Yes?
How many of you are there?
Just two?
Yes, just Ana and me.
I brought you these.
You might need it.
Oh, you are amazing.
I'll take the knife.
You keep that.
Okay, Gabriel,
we need to get that radio.
We need to get
the men out of the camp.
Copy. Stick to the plan.
You'll take us with you, right?
Yes, we're all going
to get out of here.
Right? Let's go.
Come on! Go! Go!
Get back. Get back.
Oh, my God,
they killed everybody.
Oh, we're fucked.
- The guard tower.
- Go!
-Come on.
-Come on!
Okay, wait here.
Hey.
What are you doing?
No, no.
It's okay. Trust me.
This is Sergeant
Gabriel Villanueva
of the United States Army,
requesting immediate extraction.
Over.
Copy.
Tow plane required.
I repeat, C-47 required.
-Look for the flares.
- Copy, bright light.
Contact.
Okay, go!
Go! Go! Go!
Get up.
Thanks.
Come on! Come on!
Come on!
Nowhere to run now.
Nobody is running.
Wright, come on!
-We gotta go!
-No! No!
Come on, let's go.
Mayday, mayday. This is Sergeant
Gabriel Villanueva.
-Come in. Over.
-Jonesy, help me!
Get that pole and stick it in
the ground as hard as you can.
Make it secure.
C-47 and escort en route.
Looking for Jungle Eagle. Over.
Copy that. Setting flares now.
Back up.
Copy you,
Sergeant Villanueva.
Uh, flare spotted,
Jungle Eagle .
Coming in for a closer look,
then re-approach
for extraction.
-Over.
-Here we go.
Go! Go!
Everyone in
the glider now! Let's go!
Come on, Beardy.
Let's go, everyone.
Give me a boost.
Okay, we're good! Let's go!
Extraction point identified.
Circling back.
All right, everybody,
make sure
you're strapped in good.
Hold onto each other.
Okay. We're locked in.
We're loaded into the glider.
It's going to be a rough one.
You boys take cover.
Unfriendlies closing in fast
from the west.
We're going to clear
the field for you.
Circling around
to pick you up. Standby.
Here we go. Everybody, hold on.
Grab onto something tight.
Jungle Eagle,
we're on final approach .
This is it!
Brace for impact.
Hold on!
Hold on! Hold tight!
It's up!
We're up! She's holding!
We made it!
- Holy shit.
- We made it.
We made it.
Hey guys, guys...
-You okay?
-Yes.
You okay?
You guys good?
This is Sergeant Villanueva.
We are airborne.
Copy that, Jungle Eagle .
Don't worry, lads.
We'll be back.
What is it
you've come here for?
Where is he?
My father passed away
last year, Mr. Wright.
- My condolences.
- Wait!
I want to see.
I said, I want to see!
Please.
If you insist.
Show me.
Wait!
I believe this belongs to you.
My father told me that, one day,
that a white man
will come for this.